SAM MARKHAM SOFTWARE ENGINEER

- sam.e.markham@gmail.com
- https://dev.to/sharkham
- **(**778) 387-0734
- ♥ Vancouver, BC
- in markhamsam
- Sharkham

Full stack software engineer with experience in Ruby and Javascript, including Rails and React frameworks. Developing further skills in PostgreSQL. My previous adventures include a decade of solving problems through writing, editing, critique and collaboration across many fields, from fiction and a published sociology paper to graphic novels and press releases. My blend of skills in collaboration, communication, analysis and creativity supplement my hard skills in coding. I enjoy putting my mind to a blank page and crafting something tangible and useful.

Skills

TECHNOLOGIES

Ruby

Rails

SQL

Postgres

JavaScript

Javascrip

React

Redux

HTML CSS

Node

Nokogiri

Git

Regex (Ruby, JS)

Adobe

Photoshop

InDesign

Education

Flatiron School June 2019 to May 2020 Full Stack Software Engineering, Ruby on Rails and JavaScript program

University of British Columbia Sept. 2009 to May 2015 BFA Creative Writing & Sociology 2015

Projects

Novel Tracker Apr. 2020 to Present

Github FrontEnd | Github BackEnd | Demo Video | Deployed Demo

An app for writers to keep track of their writing progress in a yearly novel writing contest

(Created for Codex Writers' Group, an online community of active speculative fiction writers)

- Developed a Rails API backend with endpoints for users, novels, badges, and badge types
 Backed the API with a Postgres database to facilitate smooth deployment to Heroku
- Backed the API with a Postgres database to facilitate smooth deployment to Herokt
- Implemented user interface using React and Redux with reactstrap for styling
- Implemented forgot/reset password functionality to prepare for live use
- Deployed backend server to Heroku and frontend to Netlify

PokéTeam Builder

Feb. 2020 to Present

Dec. 2019 to Dec. 2019

Github | Demo Video

A tactile way for Pokémon fans to quickly visualize the official heights of their favourite Pokémon

- Scraped PokéApi to populate Rails backend with information on over 300 Pokémon
- Implemented simple user interface using JavaScript click events to allow users to drag images around
- Utilized asynchronous functions to keep the API updated with changes to image position
- Styled frontend using Bootstrap to enhance user experience

Collab Writing App Github | Demo Video

A content management system for writers to keep track of group novel projects

- Utilized OAuth to allow users to sign up with Google
- Implemented has_many_through relationships in Rails to allow users to be collaborators on many novels, and also to allow novels to each have many collaborators
- · Used a role-based authorization system and helper methods to whitelist actions to specific user roles
- Utilized Action Text to enable rich text editing for novel text

Employment

Harbour Publishing | Douglas & McIntyre Book Publicist

Madeira Park, BC | Vancouver, BC Sept. 2014 to Dec. 2017, Mar. 2019 to Mar. 2020

- Utilized writing skills creating and editing a wide variety of marketing materials for 30+ books as lead
 publicist, including writing and designing press releases, event releases and posters
- Honed coordination and problem-solving skills by designing, setting up, and when necessary, troubleshooting author tours for over 20 authors across Canada and the US
- Mentored new hires and university co-op students
- Wrote a weekly newsletter for sales reps in HTML
- Gained extensive experience working remotely after relocation to Vancouver in Fall 2015

Marketing Assistant

Madeira Park, BC May 2014 to Aug. 2014

Freelance

Developmental Editor

2008 to Present

 Employed critique skills and ability to work to deadlines giving professional constructive critique and detailing both grammatical and content edits on written works, including the works of 5+ professionally published authors

Vancouver Symphony Orchestra

Lotteries Assistant

Vancouver, BC Sept. 2013 to Dec. 2013

Managed a large pool of volunteers and processed lottery tickets using the Tessitura database management system

Vancouver Chamber Choir

Marketing Assistant

Vancouver, BC June 2012 to Aug. 2012

- Coordinated the production and distribution of five brochures for the choir's educational programs
- Utilized copy-editing skills proofing the Choir's website and 2012-2013 season brochure

UBC Faculty of Applied Science

Vancouver, BC

Communications Assistant

May 2011 to Apr. 2012 the Faculty's blogs and

- Developed professional writing skills by writing articles and press releases for the Faculty's blogs and print media
- · Represented the Faculty in phone and in-person interviews with faculty, students and alumni

Publications & Conferences

Featured fiction reader, UBC Graduate Conference in Children's Literature (2012 & 2016)

Featured fiction reader, Read Out Loud, Sunshine Coast Pride's queer literary salon (2015)

Interview with Kendare Blake, author of the award-winning Anna Dressed in Blood, published in Nineteen Questions magazine (2014)

Research paper, "Bill C-389: What is the media really saying about transgender rights?" published in Sojourners: Undergraduate Journal of Sociology (2011/2012)